Petr Stepanov

Software developer. UI designer.

x stepanovps@gmail.com
√ (419) 496-86-02
↑ petrstepanov.com

Summary of Qualifications

Ph.D. graduate in physics with expertise in computer science. Strong desktop and web application software development skills. More than five years in user interface (UI) and user experience (UX) design. Seeking to apply for a software development role in the industry. Authorized to work in the US on Optional Practical Training (OPT expires February 2023). Will consider visa sponsorship offers.

Work Experience

C++ Software Developer

Thomas Jefferson National Laboratory (JLab), Newport News, VA, USA.

Jul 2020 - Current

- Applied CERN ROOT framework (C++) to perform statistical analysis of a significant amount (over 100 GB) of the raw experimental data of the <u>Kaon LT</u> experiment at JLab. <u>Link to GitHub</u>.
- Utilized SLURM environment on <u>JLab supercomputer environment</u> to run resourceful particle simulations on multiple computing nodes at the same time. This decreased the wall computation time by more than 10 times.
- Proposed and implemented RAMDisk functionality on the development environment. This lead to an over 60% increase in source code indexing time.

Software Developer • Postdoctoral Researcher

Catholic University of America (CUA), Washington, DC, USA.

Jul 2020 - Current

- Applied Machine Learning (ML) TMVA framework to perform binary classification of thousands of signals from a data acquisition (DAQ) setup. <u>Link to GitHub</u>.
- Developed a computer simulation based on the Geant4 framework (C++, CMake, Eclipse IDE, gdb) to study optical properties of a novel scintillation material to be used in the EIC detector system. <u>Link to GitHub</u>.
 - Program accounts on scintillation material properties composition, transmittance, luminescence.
 - Code reconstructs detector responce (PMT or MPPC) depending on the quantum efficiency curve.
 - Visualization of optical photon trajectories with respect to their energy or creator process.
- Enhanced debugging of the core library source code lead to opening more than <u>10 bug reports</u> on the ROOT (C++) forum.

Software Developer · Research Assistant

Bowling Green State University (BGSU), Bowling Green, OH, USA.

Aug 2014 - May 2020

- Wrote three desktop GUI programs for spectra fitting and interpretation (C++, CMake, ROOT, Qt, Java)
 - GitHub repositories contain over 10k lines of code in total: TLIST Processor, SW Calculator, RooPositron.
 - Technologies used: CMake, C++, ROOT, Fox GUI and RooFit libraries.
 - Extended default ROOT GUI library (Qt-based) to support the MVP design pattern.
- Wrote a GUI application <u>LuminApp</u> (Java, Swing) to parse and merge time-stamped data from optical spectrometer and thermometer. This increased data processing time by two orders of magnitude.
- Developed static website (Hexo, Gulp, Bootstrap) and visual identity for the <u>SelimLab</u> research group. Website has a 99% Google performance rank and features 700 ms time to interactive metrics.
- Maintained local Apache HTTP server physics.bgsu.edu hosting over 10 websites at the BGSU.
- Created website for the <u>ICPA-18</u> international conference with registration (over 150 users) and payment system workflow (WordPress, PHP, Recurly.js), and <u>landing pages</u> for events.

- Designed and built online e-commerce store <u>Sticker Store LLC</u> with static website generator (Figma, Hexo, Snipcart, Bootstrap, SASS, EJS, Node.js).
 - Improved the Google PageSpeed Insights metrics (CLS, LCP) up to 97%.
 - Created a recursive script to export over 300 products from YAML file to Google Merchant.
 - Optimized SEO. Project reached over 1400 organic monthly users.
- Made iOS application (Swift, Ulkit, storyboards) for the <u>We.Team</u> messenger (more than 3k monthly downloads in AppStore). Participated in cloud-based messenger development with enhanced file sharing capabilities (HTML, React JS, SASS).
- Migrated the landing page for <u>Sweetbridge</u> company from WordPress to Jekyll static site generator (Ruby, CSS). This resulted in a 70% improvement in the page load time.
- Developed the front-end part (Angular.js, HTML, LESS) for Lili Social network.
 - Assisted with iOS mobile application (Ionic).
 - Enabled SEO crawling of over 1000 Angular.js pages with Google bot.
- · Web design.
 - Designed logos, UI/UX prototypes (Figma, Sketch, Illustrator) and branding identity for over <u>10 different</u> companies.
 - Converted numerous design assets and mockups into responsive HTML and CSS.
 - Mocked up and integrated dozens of cross-browser responsive email templates.

Full Stack Web Developer, Web Designer

Gridnine Systems, Moscow, Russia.

Apr 2011 - Aug 2014

- Prototyped and designed interactive mockups for <u>Otixo</u> cloud file integrator (Balsamiq, Adobe Creative Suite).
 Utilized Google Web Toolkit (GWT) Model-View-Presenter (MVP) framework to develop application frontend (JavaScript, responsive CSS).
- Responsible for the front-end development of the <u>ATH American Express</u> the largest travel management company in Russia (JavaScript, Backbone.js, and RequireJS). Increased the front-end load time by over 30%.
- Implemented image processing servlets on the backend to generate banners for five different social networks (PHP, ImageMagic).
- Wireframed and sliced to web pages numerous UI/UX mockups for web applications (Balsamiq, Photoshop, HTML and CSS).

Education

Bowling Green State University (BGSU) • Ohio, USA

Aug 2014 - May 2020

Ph.D. in Photochemical Sciences • GPA 3.423. Novel developments in positron annihilation spectroscopy techniques—from experimental setups to advanced processing software. <u>View manuscript</u>.

Ohio Supercomputer Workshop • Ohio, USA

Jan 2017 - Feb 2017

Hands-on sessions in Supercomputer Essentials. Introduction to the key developments in the supercomputer field.

British Higher School of Art and Design (BHSAD) • Moscow, Russia

Dec 2011 - Feb 2012

Three-month intensive in Graphical Design and Visual Communications. Lectures and hands-on experience in graphic design. Intensive covered following subjects: brand identity, illustration principles, typography and lettering, effective advertising campaigns.

National Research Nuclear University (MEPhI) • Moscow, Russia

Aug 2014 - May 2020

B.S. and M.S. in Solid State Physics. Defect studies of neutron-irradiated nuclear power plant vessel steels by means of positron annihilation spectroscopy.

Computer Science Skills

• **Essentials**. Git, SVN, SSH, Linux, and Terminal usage. BASH scripting. IDEs: Eclipse, Xcode, Visual Studio Code (VS Code). Project management: JIRA, Trello.

- **Desktop app development**. C/C++, GNU make, CMake. Frameworks: Qt, CERN ROOT, Geant4. Java and Swing. Python.
- **Frontend**: HTML, CSS (LESS and SASS), Bootstrap, responsive web design, JavaScript and jQuery, npm, gulp, AngularJS, React.js. Google Web Toolkit. PHP and WordPress themes development.
- Backend. Node.js, EJS, Java.
- **UI/UX design**. Figma, Sketch, InVision Studio, Adobe XD, Adobe Photoshop, Adobe Illustrator, Inkscape, Blasamiq, Blender.
- Apple iOS. Fundamental Swift skills. User interface development with Ulkit and storyboards.

Professional Networks

- Discover my professional contacts on LinkedIn (200+ connections).
- Find examples of my code on GitHub (50+ repositories).
- Check out my UI design portfolio on Dribbble (50+ shots).